Finding Aid for Curtis E. Rodgers Papers, 1953 and 1962-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Curtis E. Rodgers papers 1953, 1962-1971
Rodgers, Curtis E.
2 linear feet
05144 Aa 2
Curtis E. Rodgers, an African American, served in the Detroit city government from 1962 until 1970, mostly in the Commission on Community Relations. He worked to advance the interests of African Americans in Detroit by improving education, advocating for equal housing policies, and hiring more blacks to work in municipal enterprises. The collection documents his activities and that of the various government agencies for which he worked.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Curtis E. Rodgers (donor no. 9671 ) and came to the library in 2005 and 2006, with an addition from his widow Clarice Rodgers, in 2013.
The collection is open to research.
Curtis E. Rodgers was born in Little Rock, Arkansas in 1935. He graduated from the University of Michigan with a BA in political science and did post-graduate work in business administration and law at Wayne State and the University of Detroit, respectively. In 1962 he began working for the city of Detroit in the community relations and welfare divisions. From 1966 to 1968, Rodgers worked as chief supervising assistant of community services in the Commission on Community Relations. In 1968 he was named as an aide to Detroit Mayor Jerome P. Cavanaugh. A year later, Rodgers succeeded Richard Marks as the Commission's director. In January 1970, Rodgers left the CCR to join the Legal Aid and Defenders Association. Rodgers later lived in New York City.
While working for the city of Detroit, Rodgers involved himself heavily in debates regarding civil rights and equality. Specific issues included improving blacks' access to adequate primary schooling, removing bias in housing laws, expanding city patronage to minority owned businesses, increasing minority employment rates, reforming the police force, and mitigating the racially fueled violence that plagued Detroit in the late 1960s.
Curtis E. Rodgers died July 22, 2009.
The Curtis E. Rodgers collection is comprised of three series: Personal, Detroit Commission on Community Relations, and Visual Materials. and dates from 1966 to 1971 (with one item from 1953). The series includes minutes, reports, and other agenda materials. There are also speeches, press releases, studies and subject files pertaining to the Commission on Community Relations. Subjects include employment, housing, the police force, education, and building safety.
Subjects:
Rodgers, Curtis E.; Detroit (Mich.). Commission on Community Relations.; Discrimination in employment--Michigan--Detroit.; Discrimination in housing--Michigan--Detroit.; African Americans--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series includes biographical information, awards, student papers, and materials relating to the Detroit High School Study Commission and Detroit Council for Political Education.
  - Funeral obsequy and other biographical information (Box 1)
  - Personal material (daily planner, promotion, resignation, etc.) (Box 1)
  - Student papers (Box 1)
  - Detroit Council for Political Education (Box 1)
  - Detroit High School Study Commission 1966-1967 (Box 1)
- Detroit Commission on Community Relations
  dates from 1966 to 1971 (with one item from 1953). The series includes minutes, reports, and other agenda materials. There are also speeches, press releases, studies and subject files pertaining to the Commission on Community Relations. Subjects include employment, housing, the police force, education, and building safety.
  - Affirmative Action Plans submitted by Detroit Companies 1962-1971 (Box 1)
  - Building and Safety Hiring and Promotion 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Census of Employees of the City of Detroit 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Charter Commission April 1971 (Box 1)
  - Common Council materials 1970 (Box 1)
  - Construction Trades Agreement 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Contract Compliance 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence December 5, 1962-September 3, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence July 27, 1969-December 30, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence January 2, 1970-February 10, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Court cases 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Director Turnover August 22, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Police (complaints, recruitment, and Civil Disturbance Alert System) (Box 1)
  - Education and Desegregation 1962-1970 (Box 1)
  - Employment Division 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Employment Subcommittee meetings 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Fair Neighborhood Practices Ordinance 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - Field Division 1969 (Box 1)
  - Housing Division articles and reports 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Lists 1970 (Box 1)
  - Minutes and agenda materials
    - September 1969-January 1970 (Box 1)
    - March-May 1970 (Box 1)
    - June-August 1970 (Box 2)
    - September 1970-January 1971 (Box 2)
    - February-October 1971 (Box 2)
  - Minority Contractors 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1968-1971, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Operations of Commission on Community Relations 1969 (Box 2)
  - Ordinance 206-G (Fair Employment) articles and guidelines 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Personal material (daily planner, promotion, resignation, etc.) (Box 2)
  - Plans from other cities (New York, Philadelphia, and Pittsburgh) 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Photograph of Commission members circa 1968 (Box 2)
  - Police-Community Relations Project Committee Report June 1970 (Box 2)
  - Police-Community Relations Subcommittee 1969 (Box 2)
  - Press Releases 1969 (Box 2)
  - Procedures for Commission on Community Relations (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Companies contracted with the City of Detroit 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Speeches 1969 (Box 2)
  - Transfer Summary from the Mayor's Interracial Committee on Community Relations May 14, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Awards (medals in boxes) given to Curtis Rodgers from the City of Detroit and WWJ Radio (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes photos of Detroit Commission on Community Relations staff and others along with photos and a digitized film made during the latter stages of the Detroit Riot of 1967.
  - Awards (medals in boxes) given to Curtis Rodgers from the City of Detroit and WWJ Radio; also Cavanagh campaign buttons (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Commission members circa 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Detroit Riot scenes 1967 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Film of Detroit Riot scenes 1967 (digitized) (Box 2)
Related material
Other papers of Curtis Rodgers, relating to his work with the NAACP are held by the Library of Congress.